Guide to the Kenneth M. Johnson Sermons, 1951-2010 RL.00638
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kenneth M. Johnson Sermons
1951-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Johnson, Kenneth M., 1928-
RL.00638
11 Linear Feet
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Kenneth M. Johnson Sermons were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2001-2002; additions in 2017, 2018.
Biographical Note
Retired United Methodist minister from Durham, N.C.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of typescripts of Rev. Kenneth Johnson's sermons, many containing handwritten notes and accompanying material on which the sermon topic was based. Sermons are numbered and are arranged by date, according to the church Johnson was serving at the time. The 2002 accession also contains card indices of sermons (ca. 3600 items), which arranges sermons by title, topic, and scriptures and texts. Johnson's sermons were delivered at United Methodist churches across North Carolina, including McKendree Chapel, New Mt. Vernon-Shady Grove, West Bend, Oak Summit, Asbury Memorial, Green Street, Saint Andrew's (Charlotte), Central (Mooresville), Leaksville (Eden), First (Newton), Burkhead (Winston-Salem), Aldersgate Methodist (Shelby), and Grace Methodist (Greensboro). Johnson also preached several sermons in Indonesia (1995, 1998).
Accompanying the sermons are Johnson's personal record books and bulletins from his appointed churches. The church bulletins are bound by date and church; the record books, designed for a pastor's personal use, record his annual sermons preached as well as his congregation's marriages, births, funerals, and other notes from his work as pastor at various churches. Also contains Johnson's lecture notes and reading lists from summer school and divinity courses at Duke University.
Sermons, American; Sermons, American -- 20th century; Sermons, American -- North Carolina; Sermons; Indexes (reference sources); Methodist Church -- North Carolina; Methodist Church -- Sermons -- 20th century; Johnson, Kenneth M., 1928-
- Accession 2001-0179
  - Sermons, 1951-1971
    - Nos. 1-28 Statesville District: McKendree Charge (McKendree Chapel, Williamson's Chapel, Rocky Mount), 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - Nos. 29-115 Thomasville District: New Mt. Vernon-Shady Grove Charge, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
    - Nos. 116-118 Asheboro, NC: West Bend Methodist, 1955-1960 (Box 1)
    - Nos. 119-238 Asheboro, NC: West Bend Methodist (cont.), 1955-1960 (Box 2)
    - Nos. 239-333 Asheboro, NC: West Bend Methodist (cont.), 1955-1960 (Box 3)
    - Nos. 334-350 Asheboro, NC: West Bend Methodist (cont.), 1955-1960 (Box 4)
    - Nos. 351-424 Winston-Salem, NC: Oak Summit Methodist, 1960-1964 (Box 4)
    - Nos. 425-466 Winston-Salem, NC: Oak Summit Methodist (cont.), 1960-1964 (Box 5)
    - Nos. 467-519 Asheville, NC: Asbury Memorial Methodist, 1964-1967 (Box 5)
    - Nos. 520-541 Asheville, NC: Asbury Memorial Methodist (cont.), 1964-1967 (Box 6)
    - Nos. 542-614 Winston-Salem, NC: Green Street Methodist, 1967-1971 (Box 6)
    - Nos. 615-647 Winston-Salem, NC: Green Street Methodist (cont.), 1967-1971 (Box 7)
- Accession 2002-0038
  - Sermons, 1971-1988
    - Nos. 648-687 Charlotte, NC: Saint Andrew's United Methodist, 1971-1974 (Box 8)
    - Nos. 688-732 Mooresville, NC: Central United Methodist, 1974-1977 (Box 8)
    - Nos. 733-762 Mooresville, NC: Central United Methodist (cont.) 1974-1977 (Box 9)
    - Nos. 763-833 Eden, NC: Leaksville United Methodist, 1977-1981 (Box 9)
    - Nos. 834-886 Eden, NC: Leaksville United Methodist (cont.), 1977-1981 (Box 10)
    - Nos. 887-926 Newton, NC: First United Methodist, 1981-1984 (Box 10)
    - Nos. 927-992 Newton, NC: First United Methodist (cont.), 1981-1984 (Box 11)
    - Nos. 993-1032 Winston-Salem, NC: Burkhead United Methodist, 1984-1988 (Box 11)
    - Nos. 1033-1049 Winston-Salem, NC: Burkhead United Methodist, 1984-1988 (Box 12)
- Accession 2002-0140
  - Sermons, 1985-2002
    - Nos. 1050-1150 Winston-Salem, NC: Burkhead Methodist, 1985-1988 (Box 13)
    - Nos. 1151-1164 Shelby, NC: Aldersgate Methodist, 1988 (Box 13)
    - Nos. 1165-1238 Shelby, NC: Aldersgate Methodist, 1988-1990 (Box 14)
    - Nos. 1239-1274 Greensboro, NC: Grace Methodist, 1990-1991 (Box 14)
    - Nos. 1275-1380 Greensboro, NC: Grace Methodist, 1991-1993 (Box 15)
    - Nos. 1381-1418 Greensboro, NC: Grace Methodist, 1993-1994 (Box 16)
    - Nos. 1419-1434 Medan, N. Sumatra, Indonesia, 1995 January-April (Box 16)
    - No. 1435 Rocky Mount, NC: Rocky Mount UMC, 1995 August 20 (Box 16)
    - No. 1436 Newton, NC: First Baptist Church, 1996 May 26 (Box 16)
    - No. 1437 Winston-Salem, NC: Green Street UMC, 1996 May 19 (Box 16)
    - No. 1438 Charlotte, NC: Pleasant Grove UMC, 1996 September 8 (Box 16)
    - No. 1439 Winston-Salem, NC: Oak Summit UMC, 1997 May 18 (Box 16)
    - No. 1440 Enka, NC: Francis Asbury UMC, 1997 June 29 (Box 16)
    - No. 1441 Haverhill, NH: First Congregational, 1997 August 10 1997 (Box 16)
    - No. 1442 Asheville, NC: Asbury Memorial, 1997 October 12 (Box 16)
    - Nos. 1443-1449 Jakarta, Indonesia, 1998 April-May (Box 16)
    - Nos. 1450-1452 Indonesia: Prepared but not preached, 1998 May (Box 16)
    - No. 1453 Haverhill, NH: First Congregational, 1999 August 1 (Box 16)
    - No. 1454 Bel Air, MD: Bel Air UMC, 1999 October 17 (Box 16)
    - No. 1455 Horse Shoe, NC: Cummings Memorial UMC, 2000 August 1 (Box 16)
    - No. 1456 Charlotte, NC: Pleasant Grove, 2001 September 9 (Box 16)
    - No. 1457 Holly Springs, GA: Holly Springs UMC, 2001 September 16 (Box 16)
    - No. 1458 Asheboro, NC: West Bend UMC, 2002 May 19 (Box 16)
  - Card index to sermons
    - By title, A-W (Box 20)
    - By title, X-Z (Box 17)
    - By topic, A-G (Good works) (Box 17)
    - By topic, G (Goodbye)-P (Prostitution) (Box 18)
    - By topic, P (Protection)-Z (Box 19)
    - By scriptures and texts, Genesis-John (Box 19)
    - By scriptures and texts, Genesis-John, continued; Acts-Revelation (Box 21)
- Accession 2017-0156
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains sermons 1459-1473, ranging from 2002-2010.
  Series also contains one unnumbered sermon from 1983.
  - Sermons, 1983, 2002-2010
    - (Unnumbered sermon): High Point, NC Wesley Memorial UMC, 1983 (Box 22)
      "To See the Lord, High and Lifted Up"
    - No. 1459 Holly Springs, GA: Holly Springs United Methodist Church, 2002 (Box 22)
      Sermon: "Called to be Saints"
      Includes program from Holly Springs United Methodist Church.
    - No. 1460 Medan, North Sumatra, Indonesia: Wesley Methodist Church, 2003 (Box 22)
      Sermon titled: "Good News for our Troubled World"
      Includes program for services at Wesley Memorial church, photocopies of newspaper articles on Jessica Lynch, the Iraqi city of Basra, printouts of emails, and a printed anti-war statement.
    - No. 1461 Jakarta, Indonesia: Wesley Methodist Church, 2003 August 10 (Box 22)
      Sermon entitled "Saved People Act Like it" along with church program.
    - No. 1462 Holly Springs, Georgia: Holly Springs United Methodist Church, 2004 January 25 (Box 22)
      Contains sermon entitled "Clear me from Hidden Faults", church newsletter, and program from services with annotations.
    - No. 1463 Holly Springs, Georgia: Holly Springs United Methodist Church, 2004 April 18 (Box 22)
      Contains sermond entitled "Rainbow Living", correspondence, and church programs.
    - No. 1464 Rosman and Brevard, North Carolina: Rosman and Selica United Methodist Churches, 2004 October 24 (Box 22)
      Contains sermon entitled "Be All That You Can Be" which was preached at two churches, the Selica and Rosman United Methodist churches. Folder also contains programs from these churches
    - No. 1465 Medan, North Sumatra, Indonesia: Wesley Methodist Church, 2005 October 23 (Box 22)
      Includes sermon entitled "When We Are Put To The Test", program for church, correspondence, and trip itinerary for visit to Medan.
    - No. 1466 Jakarta, Indonesia: Wesley Methodist Church, 2005 October 30 (Box 22)
      Includes sermon entitled "How To Be Your Best Self", church program, and photocopies of excerpts of the Book of Matthew.
    - No. 1467 Rosman and Brevard, North Carolina: Rosman and Selica United Methodist Church, 2005 November 13 (Box 22)
      Includes sermon entitled "Rosman/Selica: Churches of Encouragement" and program from Selica United Methodist Church.
    - No. 1468 Rosman, North Carolina: Rosman United Methodist Church, 2006 April 23 (Box 22)
      Includes sermon entitled "A Walk That Changed The World" and church program.
    - No. 1469 Salisbury, North Carolina: First United Methodist Church, 2007 May 6 (Box 22)
      Includes sermon entitled "How To Spot A Christian", church programs, correspondence, and printouts of Bible verses.
    - No. 1470 Baltimore, Maryland: Mt. Vernon and Hampden United Methodist Churches, 2007 October 21 (Box 22)
      Includes two versions of sermon entitled "Becoming a Competent Christian." The first was preached in Baltimore, Maryland. A second version of the sermon, preached in the Wesley Methodist Church in Jakarta, Indonesia on February 3, 2008. Also contains programs from the Baltimore churches, a copy of "The Hampden Herald", and email correspondence.
    - No. 1471 Jakarta, Indonesia: Grace Methodist Church, 2008 February 10 (Box 22)
      Includes sermon entitled "Forgiveness Brings Us Joy" and church progam.
    - No. 1472 Selica, North Carolina: Selica United Methodist Church, 2008 November 30 (Box 22)
      Includes sermon entitled "Grace and Truth - For Such A Time As This" and church program.
    - No. 1473 Rocky Mount, North Carolina: Rocky Mount United Methodist Church, 2009 August 16 (Box 22)
      Includes three versions of sermon entitled "For What Do We Pray?"
      The first was preached at Rocky Mount United Methodist Church on August 16, 2009. The second was preached at the Selica United Methodist Church on September 27, 2009. The third was preached at the Hampden United Methodist Church on October 31, 2010.
      Item also contains programs from above churches.
- Accession 2018-0036 and 2018-0061, 1951-1993
  - Church bulletins, 1951-1992
    Bound volumes of bulletins from different North Carolina churches, collected while Johnson served as pastor.
    - West Bend Methodist Church, Asheboro, 1955-1958 (Box 23)
    - West Bend Methodist Church, Asheboro, 1958-1960 (Box 25)
    - Oak Summit Methodist Church, Winston-Salem, 1960-1962 (Box 25)
    - Oak Summit Methodist Church, Winston-Salem, 1962-1964 (Box 25)
    - Asbury Memorial Methodist Church, Asheville, 1964-1967 (Box 23)
    - Green Street United Methodist Church, Winston-Salem, 1967-1969 (Box 25)
    - Green Street United Methodist Church, Winston-Salem, 1969-1971 (Box 24)
    - St. Andrew's United Methodist Church, Charlotte, 1971-1974 (Box 25)
    - Central United Methodist Church, Mooresville, 1974-1975 (Box 23)
    - Central United Methodist Church, Mooresville, 1976-1977 (Box 25)
    - Leaksville United Methodist Church, Eden, 1977-1979 (Box 23)
    - Leaksville United Methodist Church, Eden, 1979-1981 (Box 23)
    - First United Methodist Church, Newton, 1981-1984 (Box 23)
    - Burkhead United Methodist Church, Winston-Salem, 1984-1986 (Box 25)
    - Burkhead United Methodist Church, Winston-Salem, 1986-1988 (Box 23)
    - Aldersgate United Methodist Church, Shelby, 1988-1990 (Box 25)
    - Grace United Methodist Church, Greensboro, 1990-1992 (Box 25)
    - Grace United Methodist Church, Greensboro, 1992-1994 (Box 23)
  - Duke Divinity School notes, 1951-1958
    - Lecture notes, 1952-1953, 1958 (Box 26)
      Bound volumes kept by Johnson with tabs for each course's lecture notes and readings. Includes topics like theology, pastoral care (including medical perspectives and lectures on mental health and counseling), church history, speech, and preaching practice sessions.
    - Duke University summer school notes, 1951 (Box 24)
      2 binders with notes for child psychology, learning/educational psychology, history of education
  - Johnson's personal logbooks, 1951-1993
    - Pocket record books, 1951-1993 (Box 24)
      42 pocket record books for pastoral duties including lists of baptisms, marriages, funerals, and Johnson's sermons delivered (with text numbers)